Guide to the Spain Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Spain collection
1400-1891
1600-1699
MS 1777
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.5
(16 boxes)
A collection of correspondence; government documents, including reports, commissions, decrees, and awards; church documents; and writings and poems from Spain on civil, military, economic, religious, and social topics.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials have been assembled from various collections and acquired from several individuals. They include materials transferred from the Latin American Collection Curator, Yale University Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 249 instead of the originals.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection is available on microfilm from Gale Group, Farmington Hills, Michigan.
Scope and Contents
A collection of correspondence; government documents, including reports, commissions, decrees, and awards; church documents; and writings and poems from Spain on civil, military, economic, religious, and social topics.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two parts: materials in each part are arranged by date.
Mexico -- History -- Wars of Independence, 1810-1821; South America -- History -- Wars of Independence, 1806-1830; Spain -- Church history; Spain -- Colonies; Spain -- History -- Bourbons, 1700-; Spain -- History -- Charles III, 1759-1788; Spain -- History -- Charles IV, 1788-1808; Spain -- History -- Ferdinand VI, 1746-1759; Spain -- History -- Ferdinand VII, 1813-1833; Spain -- History -- House of Austria, 1516-1700; Spain -- History -- Napoleonic Conquest, 1808-1813; Spain -- History -- Philip III, 1598-1621; Spain -- History -- Philip IV, 1621-1665; Spain -- History -- Philip V, 1700-1746; Spain -- History -- Revolution, 1820-1823; Ayala, Manuel José de, 1728-1805; Campillo y Cosío, José del, 1693-1743; González de Cellorigo, Martín; Jovellanos, Gaspar de, 1744-1811; Olivares, Gaspar de Guzmán, conde-duque de, 1587-1645; Pérez, Antonio, -1611
- Original accession
  - Part I, 1400-1768
    Scope and Contents
    Part I is 4.5 linear feet; the majority is comprised of both originals and copies of materials from Spain. The collection includes state documents such as decrees, ordinances and reports; ecclesiastical texts; correspondence; accounts of events; political writings; and literary texts. They cover a broad period of Spanish history, from the beginning of the fifteenth century to the middle of the eighteenth century. The texts document important events and aspects of the reigns of Philip III, Philip IV, Philip V, Ferdinand VI and Charles III.
    On the reign of King Philip III (1598-1621), the collection includes letters by the Duke of Lerma, the powerful private secretary (privado) to the king; documents related to state loans; and memorials. Memorials constitute outstanding sources for studying the political, social and economic conditions of the Spanish monarchy in the two first decades of the seventeenth century. Although a long tradition of writing memorials existed in Spain, Philip III's reign was particularly rich in the composition of such texts. They addressed such issues as the origin of the "decadence" of Spain, and important political and economic problems and their solutions. There are also texts on the conduct of foreign policy by Antonio Pérez; royal policy towards Portuguese "conversos" by Martín González de Cellorigo; and the duties of the king's private secretary (privado) by Pedro Maldonado. The education of the young King Phillip III was an important issue during his reign. The "Empresas," by Juan de Mora, a book written to instruct the king on moral and political principles necessary for ruling, is beautifully illustrated with numerous drawings and is a splendid example of Spanish emblematic literature.
    Documents on the reign of King Philip IV (1621-1665) are the most numerous of the collection. The main political and social events of that period, including the death of King Philip III; the political downfall of three major figures of the reign of King Philip III: the duke of Lerma, the duke of Osuna, and the marquis of Siete Iglesias; the ceremonies proclaiming Philip IV of Spain; the political career of the duke of Olivares, the private secretary (privado) of the king; the plan for a matrimonial alliance between Spain and England; the economic efforts of the Spanish crown to finance its participation in the Thirty Years War; the Castilian monetary reforms; the Spanish intervention in the Netherlands war; and the political relations between the Spanish crown and its Italian allies in Milan, are described in handwritten and printed texts.
    Important aspects of the history of the reigns of three Bourbon monarchs, Philip V (1700-1746), Ferdinand VI (1746-1759) and Charles III (1559-1788) are also documented in the collection. With no direct descendants, King Charles II named Philip, Duke of Anjou, a grandson of King Louis XIV of France, as his successor. The election of a French prince was not recognized by other European states, which had potential candidates of their own for the Spanish throne and were concerned about the expansion of French power on the continent. The war of the Spanish Succession and the efforts of Philip to consolidate his rule are illustrated in an extensive account of the period from 1712 to 1725, entitled "History of the reign of King Philip V of Spain," and in other documents. Once the war was concluded, Philip started an ambitious program to reform the social, political and economic structures of the Spanish monarchy. The so-called "Bourbon Reforms" encouraged crown ministers and other citizens to develop and write projects and plans to encourage the social and economic development of Spain and its empire. Interesting examples of such writings are: "España despierta" and "Nuevo sistema de gobierno económico para la América," by José del Campillo y Cosio, a famous minister of Philip V.
    The Bourbon Reforms were continued by Philip V's successors, Ferdinand VI and Charles III. Additional informative examples of reform plans and projects, from the reign of Ferdinand VI, include "Reflexiones ...sobre los medios que se pueden tomar para el fomento de fábricas de todas especies y del comercio interno y externo de España" by Juan Casaus, and "Proyecto...para fomento del comercio, agricultura y fábricas de estos reinos" by Francisco Pavia. There are also various documents on tax reform during Ferdinand's reign, and on the relationship between the Inquisition and local powers. Of particular note regarding Charles III's reign (1759-1788) is "Aniceto a Cándido," a discourse on the need to reform Spain; and an extensive "Memorial," addressed to the king, on the long controversy between the Society of Jesus and prelates and secular clergy over the payment of tithes. In addition, there are documents on the crown's attempt to exercise tight control over the Spanish Catholic Church.
    - Title: Royal grant. Place: Valladolid. Description: Copy of a royal grant by Henry III, king of Castile, to the village of Balmaceda. Needing funds for the war against Portugal, the king had given his treasurer, Juan de Herrera, lordship over Balmaceda. In turn, Herrera had paid 15,000 florins to the king. In this grant, Henry III granted 7,500 florins to Balmaceda to be used by the village in its attempt to buy out Herrera. With this grant, the king expected that the village could obtain its freedom from the dominion of Herrera, and become part of the royal patrimony., 1400 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Copia de las capitulaciones que se hizieron entre el ... Rey don Felipe Segundo con el conde de San Segundo." Place: Hampton Court. Description: Printed copy of a text containing the agreements (capitulaciones) between Gómez Suarez de Figueroa, general lieutenant of Milan, and Troilo de Rossi, count of San Segundo. In this document, Gómez Suares granted military protection, tax exemptions, and commercial privileges to Troilo de Rossi, a Milan noble., 1555 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - Author: Sotomayor, Agustín de. Title: Texts. Place: Spain. Description: A Spanish mineralogist, Agustín de Sotomayor lived in Mexico for some years, and returned to Spain in 1574. In Spain, he explored mines by royal commission, and made experiments for the extraction of minerals. This volume contains an original and copies (in English) of texts by Agustín de Sotomayor: "Benefiçios de metales de plata" (handwritten and signed by author), "Translation of extracts from Noticia histórica documentada de las célebres minas de Guadalcanal," and "A Letter from Augustin de Sotomayor to his majesty upon the method to be followed in the discovery of mines and the manner of working them.", 1555-1573 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Memorial que el cardenal don Francisco de Mendoza y Bobadilla dio al rey Phelipe 2 sobre la deçendençia de las casas más prinçipales de España." Description: Copy of an extensive report by Cardinal Francisco de Mendoza y Bobadilla, bishop of Burgos, to King Philip II of Spain, about the origins of Spanish noble families., 1560 November (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by King Philip II. Place: Madrid. Description: Letter by King Philip II to the count of Santa Gadea, adelantado of Castile and general captain of galleys on the Andalucian coasts. In this letter, the king asked the count to obtain more news about an attack the British fleet was preparing against Spain., 1588 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - Author: García, Pablo? Title: "Modo de procesar en el Tribunal de la Santa Inquisición." Description: Book containing a copy of the ordinances to be followed by Spanish Inquisition tribunals in judicial proceedings. Includes detailed instructions on how to conduct interrogatories and torments, and issue sentences and edicts. Includes an index by subject., Circa1591 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Consult by the Council of Italy. Place: Madrid? Description: Consult by the council of Italy, addressed to King Philip II, on the state of Milan, a Spanish dominion in Italy. In this document, the council of Italy proposed different reforms for the political and economic government of that territory., 1597 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Royal decree. Place: Madrid. Description: Printed copy of a royal decree by Prince Philip (future King Philip III) ordering the creation of a general militia for the defense of Spain. Details the composition, duties and privileges of the members of the militia. The document includes the authorization (licencia) by the count of Puñonrostro to Lázaro de Hojeda for printing the royal decree for one month., 1598 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - Author: Pérez, Antonio. Title: "El conocimiento de las naciones." Description: Antonio Pérez was secretary to King Philip II and one of the most controversial political figures in the second half of the sixteenth century in Spain. In this extensive copy of a memorial written from his exile, Pérez advises the young King Philip III how to rule the dominions of the Spanish monarchy in Europe and America, and how to conduct foreign policy with France, the Turkish Empire, the Italian states, and the Papal state., 1598 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Legal writ. Place: Spain. Description: Copy of a legal writ related to the judicial proceedings of Alvaro de Ulloa, as agent of the minors Alvaro and Teresa de Ulloa, citizens of Caceres, against García de Loayza, dean of the Cathedral of Plasencia, over the payment of a quit-rent (censo.), [15--] (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Documents related to Margaret of Austria, Queen of Spain. Places: Valladolid, San Lorenzo. Description: Printed and handwritten copies of five documents related to the testament of the Margaret of Austria, Queen of Spain. Includes: "Facultad que el rey nuestro señor dio a su magestad de la reyna, que esté en el cielo, para testar de dozientos mil ducados" (4 September 1601); "Cláusula del testamento de la reyna nuestra señora en favor del Colegio de la Compañía de Jesús de Salamanca" (n.d.); "Copia del codicilio que hizo la reyna nuestra señora" (n.d.); "Juramento del Padre Ricardo Haller sobre el codicilio de la reyna nuestra señora que aya gloria" (13 October 1611); "La reyna nuestra señora, que esté en el cielo, su testamento", (undated) 1601-1611 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Possesión que la magetad del rey nuestro señor don Phelipe Terzero tomó de el canonicato y prebenda de esta santa yglesia de León." Place: Leon. Description: In recognition of his victory over the Muslims in the battle of Clavijo, the pope had granted to King Ramiro I and his successors the possession of an ecclesiastical canonry at the cathedral of Leon. This text is an account of the ceremony at which King Philip III assumed title to the canonry on 2 February 1602. Includes a description of the travel of King Philip III and his retinue from Valladolid to Leon., 1602 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
    - Title: The re-establishment of the Society of Jesus in France. Place: Burdeos. Description: Printed account of the re-establishment of the Society of Jesus in France. In this text, apparently addressed to the Spanish Jesuits, an anonymous French Jesuit describes the social opposition to the Society of Jesus in France, the attitude of the French king towards the order, and the educational and religious tasks undertaken by the Jesuits after the French Parliament issued the edict of re-establishment., 1604 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Ynstrucción que se dio... A los quatro secretarios del Consejo de Indias y al escribano de Cámara." Place: Valladolid. Description: Copy of a royal instruction concerning the duties of secretaries and notary of the Council of the Indies., 1604 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 14, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Ordinances for the king's service. Place: Madrid. Description: Copies of different ordinances, issued between 1608 and 1648, for the service of the Spanish king. Includes detailed instructions on the protocol and duties to be followed by the members of the royal house including secretaries, lords of the bed-chamber, valets-de-chambre, guards, and servants., 1721 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by the duke of Lerma. Place: Madrid. Description: Letter by the duke of Lerma, to Secretary Matienzo, instructing him to order the condestable of Castile, governor of Milan, to use a seal (estampa), rather than a signature, in making payments to soldiers in the infantry, chivalry and fortresses., 1612 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by the duke of Lerma. Description: Copy of a letter by the duke of Lerma, to the marquis of Boza, concerning King Philip III's reaction to the baptism of the marquis' grandson., [ca 1612] (Box 2, Folder 17, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Acuerdo en que el reyno señala la cantidad con que se ha de servir a su magestad." Description: Printed texts related to a loan to support the military campaign of the Spanish army in Flanders and Germany. The texts concern the collection of the loan in the American and Spanish territories., 1617-1623 (Box 2, Folder 18, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Documents on Cádiz fortifications. Places: Cádiz, Madrid. Description: Two documents, a printed decree by the king and instructions addressed to Juan de Fuente Hurtado, concerning the collection of funds for the construction of fortifications on the Cádiz Bay., 1617-1627 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Consulta que hiço el Consejo Real de Castilla al señor Phelipe Tercero sobre la conservación de sus reynos." Place: Madrid. Description: Report by the members of the Council of Castile, to the king, on the causes of the depopulation of Spain., 1619 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
    - Author: González de Cellorigo, Martín. Place: Madrid. Title: Memorial to the king. Description: Memorial by Martín González de Cellorigo, addressed to the king, on the royal policy towards Jews in Spain. Cellorigo believed Jews should be tolerated due to their economic and social significance, but proposed that they be converted to Christianity., 1619 July 5 (Box 3, Folder 21, Reel 2U)
    - Author: Marquis of Montenegro. Title: Memorials. Place: Madrid. Description: Copies of two memorials by the marquis of Montenegro, addressed to the king, concerning the conduct of foreign policy: the first, on the alliances with Italian nobles; the second, on military strategy to follow in the war taking place in Germany., 1620 (Box 3, Folder 22, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Copia de una carta que vino en pliego del Obispo de Gaeta, para don Juan de la Sal, obispo de Bona." Place: Naples. Description: Printed letter by the bishop of Gaeta, to Juan de la Sal, bishop of Bona, narrating the end of duke of Osuna's tenure as viceroy of Naples. In this text, the author defends the government of the duke and attributes his downfall to political intrigue., 1620 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 2U)
    - Title: Royal decree by the king. Place: Madrid. Description: Very damaged copy (difficult to read) of a royal decree by the king concerning Fernando Carrillo., 1621 April 23 (Box 3, Folder 24, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Acuerdo que se toma de parte de su magestad." Place: Madrid. Description: In 1620 the Spanish crown confiscated gold and silver which had been transported from Spanish America. This document is an agreement between the crown and the deputies of the Consulate of Seville, Pedro de Avendaño Villela and Fernando López Ramírez, over how the crown was to pay back the money it seized., 1621 July 6 (Box 3, Folder 25, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Premática. Places: San Lorenzo, Madrid. Description: Printed royal decree (premática) by the king, issued on 7 October 1621, concerning quit-rents and state pensions (juros). Includes a text which notes that the decree was proclaimed on 8 October 1621 in Madrid. (Box 3, Folder 26, Reel 2U)
    - Author: Nájera, Hernando de. Title: "Relación del día." Place: Seville. Description: Printed account of the ceremony in Seville proclaiming Philip IV king of Spain. Describes, in detail, the participants, the ceremonial procession, and the decorations of public buildings., 1621 (Box 3, Folder 27, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Verdadera relación." Place: Seville. Description: Printed account of the ceremony in Madrid proclaiming Philip IV king of Spain, and the funeral held in memory of Philip III, at the Church of Saint Jerome in Madrid., 1621 (Box 3, Folder 28, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Relación de avisos." Place: Seville. Description: Seventeenth-century printed texts containing news (avisos) on politics, wars and social events are considered to be early forms of journalism. In Spain and its American colonies, these texts were printed and circulated widely. This "relación" includes news from Rome, Flanders, Sicily, Germany, France, Florence and Algeria., 1621 (Box 3, Folder 29, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Relación de la muerte de ...don Felipe Tercero." Description: Printed biography of King Philip III. The account focuses on the religious piety and death of the monarch, and includes brief references to the beginnings of Philip IV's rule and the death of the great duke of Florence., 1621 (Box 3, Folder 30, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Decreto que el rey don Felipe Quarto." Place: Seville. Description: Printed copy of a decree by King Philip IV ordering the establishment of an assembly (junta) for the moral reform of society. Includes an account of the funeral of Philip III held at the royal palace in Madrid, and the transportation of the body of the king from Madrid to the royal burial site at San Lorenzo del Escorial monastery., 1621 (Box 3, Folder 31, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Relación." Place: Madrid? Description: Account of the death of Philip III and of the events which occurred in the Spanish court after his death. Includes some references to the French court and the war in the Netherlands., [ca.1621] (Box 3, Folder 32, Reel 2U)
    - Author: Gasco? Torquemada, Gregorio. Title: "Nacimiento, vida, prisión y muerte de don Rodrigo Calde[rón], marqués de siete iglesias." Description: Rodrigo Calderón, marquis of Siete Iglesias, was a member of the circle of the duke of Lerma, the powerful minister of King Philip III. After the political downfall of the duke, Calderón was prosecuted by royal order. This is an account of Calderón's stay in prison and public execution., [ca.1621] (Box 3, Folder 33, Reel 2U)
    - Title: Letter by the duke of Lerma. Place: Valladolid. Description: Letter by the duke of Lerma, to King Philip IV, accepting that 72,000 ducados of his rent from Sicily had been confiscated by the crown. The rent had been a grant by King Philip III to the duke of Lerma., [ca.1621] April 13 (Box 3, Folder 34, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Glosas". Description: Paper containing copies of two compositions in verse and a text on the duke of Lerma. The first composition is entitled "Anda niño anda, que Dios te lo manda," and consists of political advice addressed to the young King Philip IV; the second composition, "Pues agua subes Carrillo," alludes to the relationship between the count-duke of Olivares and Fernando Carrillo. The third text is a full description of the noble titles and posts held by the duke of Lerma., [1621?] (Box 3, Folder 35, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Capitulaciones que ofrece el rey de la Gran Bretaña en orden de los casamientos de el Príncipe de Gales con la Infanta de España." Place: Madrid? Description: Copy of the proposals by the king of England, addressed to the pope, to obtain the papal approval for the marriage of the prince of Wales (future King Charles II of England) to the princess of Spain. Includes the pope's responses to the proposals., 1622 October (Box 3, Folder 36, Reel 2U)
    - Title: Royal decree and instruction. Place: Madrid. Description: Two printed documents: the first, a royal decree by the king, issued on 14 January 1622, ordering the presidents of audiencias, viceroys, corregidores, governors, judges, alcaldes, and ministers of the royal treasury to submit inventories of their properties to the crown before assuming positions in the royal administration; the second, an instruction by the king, issued on 21 January 1622, explaining to those appointed to posts in the royal administration how to prepare property inventories. (Box 3, Folder 37, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Copia de los tres capítulos últimos de la carta relación de los puertos." Place: Burgos. Description: Copy of a letter by a Spanish prelate to the king warning him about the presence of British heretics in Spain, and suggesting the nomination of visitors and overseers to administer justice in Castile., 1623 January 3 (Box 3, Folder 38, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Capítulos de reformación." Place: Madrid. Description: Printed copy of a royal decree by the king ordering the establishment of "erarios y montes de piedad." Describes the regulations for their functioning., 1623 February 10 (Box 3, Folder 39, Reel 2U)
    - Title: Letter by James I, king of England. Description: Letter by James I, king of England, to Gaspar de Guzmán, count-duke of Olivares, expressing gratitude for the reception given to his son, the prince of Wales, and the marquis of Buckingham during their stay in Spain., 1623 March 29 (Box 3, Folder 40, Reel 2U)
    - Title: "Relación verdadera de la procesión y solenes fiestas que se celebraron en Roma a la elección del nuevo pontífice...Urbano VIII." Place: Madrid. Description: Printed biography of Urban VIII, elected pope in 1623. Includes brief descriptions of the ceremonies held in Rome upon his election. (Box 3, Folder 41, Reel 2U)